so i've gotten into wool hangings
recently i find them super enjoyable to
make i
love the way they look and i've been
having a really great time and once i
started posting more about them i
noticed that you guys have
plenty of questions so i thought i'd
make a video answering you guys top
questions about how to make wool
hangings so these are two of my most
recent wool hangings the patterns for
both of these are going to be linked in
the description if you want to make them
for yourself and for the one on the
right i did an
entire knot with me video where you can
watch the entire process of me making
this bracelet from start to finish and
i'll leave that linked in the card and
in the description if you want to watch
that as well in this video i'm going to
be covering alpha while hanging
specifically because i don't really have
experience with normal wall hangings and
there are slight differences although
probably the majority of what i say here
is going to apply to normal wall
hangings as well
i still would rather focus my attention
on alphas specifically because that's
just what i have experience with there's
gonna be timestamps in the description
of this video so you can skip around and
get to the topic that you want to see
covered but with all that said
let's jump into it so as you can see
wall hangings are made on these
wooden sticks they are called wooden
dowels and this is what wall hangings at
least in the world of friendship
bracelets are typically made on
these are the variety that i got got a
pack of 100 off of amazon they're 15
centimeters long with a diameter of four
millimeters and they're nothing special
just a pack of wooden dowels so as i
mentioned i got mine off amazon i've
heard from other people that you can
also get them in craft stores sometimes
even building stores sell wooden dowels
and on places online but you also don't
have to use a wooden dowel you can use
anything that you feel like a lot of
people use the same techniques for
keychains for example
i've seen people use pencils even
toothpicks although i would be careful
with those because they can snap quite
easily
same people use knitting needles
basically anything that's straight and
there's the right diameter and length
for you feel free to use whatever you
want right so let's talk about patterns
with these two wall hangings i was
pretty lucky because the pattern itself
was basically all i wanted to make so i
didn't need to cut the pattern at all
but there are still things that you want
to keep in mind when looking at the
pattern to create a wall hanging so
let's go over them so let's look at the
easiest example this mushroom house
as i said when creating this wool
hanging i wanted to use the entirety of
the pattern so i didn't actually need to
cut the pattern
into pieces to make it fit the design
with that out of the way you need to
focus on the dimensions
figure out which way you want to create
your design vertically or horizontally
for this specific pattern the case was
pretty obvious i wanted to make it
vertically so that the mushroom top is
at the top and the mushroom bottom is at
the bottom
you want to pay very close attention to
the dimensions of the pattern in this
case it's 49 by 51 and you need to
determine which of that is going to be
the number of base strings and which is
going to be the number of rows
in this specific case the number of base
strings is 49 and the number of rows is
51.
since the design is longer than it is
wide let's look at the other pattern
once again for this pattern i wanted to
create the entirety of the design so i
didn't need to cut anything but here the
situation with the orientation is a
little bit different i wanted to create
the design as it is in the preview of
the pattern so that the stingray is
horizontal
and with the dimensions of 29 by 43 this
pattern is wider so the 43 is going to
be the number of base strings and 29 the
number of rows however on this website
if you look down on the actual pattern
broken down into knots it flips the
pattern on its side
and that's not how i want to create the
design for the wall hanging so
pay attention to the dimensions and make
sure to figure out which of those
you want to be the base strings and
which you want to be the rows because
that is what determines the orientation
of the pattern whether it be horizontal
or
vertical personally i prefer reading
alpha patterns in the not
pattern version but since the website
defaults to making the shorter side the
number of bass strings this doesn't fit
me in this case because that flips the
pattern on its side and so for this
pattern i had to resort to following the
grid pattern which isn't a problem
because you can still follow that
pattern if you know how to make alpha
patterns and if you don't you should
watch my tutorial on that which is
separate and will be linked in the card
and in the description it's not a
problem it's just something that you
need to keep in mind but what if i do
want to cut a pattern let's look at this
one for example
this pattern has a lot of background
rows too many for my liking and because
the pattern preview in the knotted
format is also flipped on its side and i
want to make this horizontally rather
than vertically i need to read the grid
pattern to create this design what i
would recommend doing in this situation
is simply taking a screenshot you could
just remember how many knots you want to
leave on either side and in this case i
would leave one or two
rows either side but if you rely solely
on your memory you run the risk of
making a mistake so i would recommend
just taking a screenshot and physically
just cutting out the number of rows that
you need
make sure to count several times how
many base strings you're going to
require especially if you cut your
pattern because nothing is more annoying
in making bracelets than when you start
making something and realize that your
number of bass strings is incorrect so
make sure to
check count and double check so talking
a little bit further about dimensions
let's move back to this pattern so for
this pattern the dimensions are 29 by 43
as i mentioned previously based on which
of those dimensions you decide is going
to be the base strings that determines
the orientation of your pattern
in this specific case if i want the
stingray to be horizontal
as i showed in the woohen that i
eventually created i would take the 43
to be the number of bass strings and you
might be hearing 43
realizing that it's an odd number and
thinking to yourself how would i
attach an odd number of strings to my
dowel in fact it's a good thing when you
have an odd number of bass strings
because you also need a leading string
i tend to make my bass strings and my
leading strings the same color at least
the leading string for the first row and
the background and so it ends up being a
cohesive color for the top row for me
you don't have to do this but if you do
take separate colors
the two leftmost strings would have to
be the same color because
you need one for the base string and one
for the leading string i'll get more
into that when i actually demonstrate
but what i'm saying is that when you
have an odd number of bass strings
on your wall hanging that's a good thing
because you also need a bass string
which adds one string to the mix
making an even number which is easier to
attach to wool hanging so you might be
thinking what if i need an even number
of bass strings i still need a leading
string and that makes it an odd number
yes and that's a little bit annoying but
it's something that we can work with and
i'll get into that in one of the next
sections all right so now that we've
talked about our patterns let's talk
about our strings and how to attach them
but first
how long do you need the strings to be
this all depends on personal preference
really and
how tight you make your knots it's kind
of easy to estimate
how long a pattern is going to be if
you've made any alpha pattern before
especially if you've made alpha patterns
with the string type that you're about
to use
you can just take a ruler attach it to
whatever you've already created
and see how many rows are in one
centimeter in my case it's exactly six
rows
so i knot at a length of six rows per
centimeter you can then look back at
your pattern
see how many rows you need to make for
that design and calculate how long
your design will be so you definitely
need at least that amount of length i
would also add probably another seven to
ten
centimeters to make the ties depending
on what kind of tie you make you might
need more i'll talk more about that at
the end and then i'd probably
also add another 10 centimeters purely
for grip you're not really going to use
that amount of string you're probably
going to end up cutting it off but you
do need some amount of grip to actually
be able to knot the pattern
if you want to use your strings as
efficiently as possible you're going to
end up with
tiny little short strings at the very
end which is going to be very annoying
to work with and might damage your
design
skewing it a little bit so i would
definitely leave some for grip and yes
technically it's a waste of string
but keep the scraps you can use your
scraps in other projects
in fact i did an entire video dedicated
to how you can reuse your scraps in
friendship braces i'll leave that video
also linked in the card and in the
description so you can watch that later
so they're not really going to waste and
you really do need something to grip
onto so
it's all personal preference try and
figure out how much you're going to need
if you're unsure i would recommend going
with a little bit of a longer side
just to be safe but you also have to
make sure
to double whatever calculations you've
made because you're going to fold your
strings
in half essentially creating two so if
you've decided that you want say 30
centimeters make that 60 because you're
then going to fold it to create two
strings of 30. and
not only that but make sure that one of
your strings is
extra long so all of my strings meet at
a point on this side but on the other
side i've got one string that is extra
extra long and that's the one that's
going to be the leading string and you
want that one to be extra long since you
know you're going to use it more and
you're going to have to end up replacing
it eventually anyway so you just want to
make it extra long too
to avoid replacing it earlier on all
right so let's talk about
how to attach these strings to the dowel
i mentioned this already before but
count your strings count the strings
that you have
count the strings that you need in the
pattern count them count them again and
then count them again because it is
so annoying when you're starting to make
a design and you realize that you've
miscalculated either on the pattern or
when you were cutting your strings it is
the worst feeling in bracelet making so
definitely
definitely try to avoid that by counting
on your pattern and then
on your strings multiple times all right
so the knots that we're going to be
using are the
luxe head knots which i will be
demonstrating here but if you need a
more in-depth look on how to make those
knots and other types of knots i did a
basic knots video
a while ago and in that video i go into
real detail about how to make these
knots which will also be linked in the
card and in the description all right
you want to start by taking the longest
string that you created
the one that's extra long because it's
going to be your leading string
you want to put the shorter side on the
left and the longer side on the right
is i'm going to take your dowel you're
going to put the strings behind the
dowel
then take this loop flip it over
grab these two strings and pull them
through that loop
and then you're simply going to tighten
and there you go you've attached your
strings to your dowel the shorter string
should be on the left the longest string
should be on the right this is if you're
following the straight edge technique or
alphas where you do backward forward
knots on the left side
if you're not doing that then the longer
one will be on the left since you're
just going to go in forward knots but
because i am the longer one is going on
the right since i'm going to start with
a backward forward knot
and only then go to the right and
forward knots hope that makes sense
if it doesn't i explain the straightedge
technique in my alpha tutorial as well
in more detail with that done you're
gonna take every single other string
and do the same so all of the strings
you cut you're gonna take one by one and
you're gonna do lark's head knots
onto the dowel attaching them one by one
so let me show you once again
you wanna take this loop put it behind
the dowel you then want to flip the loop
over grab the two strings and pull them
through the loop and then simply tighten
and then you can move that to the left
and now you've got four strings all
right so i'm gonna go attach
every single one of these drinks that i
cut and i'll be right back with you
[Music]
so once you've attached all of your
strings you need to attach your dowel to
your workspace
and this is how i do it i make sure to
attach any strings that i'm going to
need within the first few rows to the
back of the surface
behind the dowel and then i simply just
attach the dowel with
two strips of tape and that way i can
pull on it not too tightly but i can and
i can start working on my design
as i mentioned the leading string is
going to be the second string if you're
following the straight edge technique
and you're going to go in with a
backward forward knot
and then with forward knots following
your pattern at this point i can't
really help you you just need to follow
the design and if you don't know how to
make alpha patterns and if you don't
know how to follow them
as i mentioned previously i have a
separate tutorial on that which is
linked in the description so i mentioned
i would talk about this later on in the
video and now is the time what do you do
if you've got an extra bass string it's
basically the same thing
as with a new string for example if i'm
going to be tying in a new string within
the first couple of rows
i'm going to have this little tail
sticking out the back same thing for
when you have an extra string
if you've got an extra string that you
don't need simply pull it out
and put it behind your wall hanging make
the make the knots
excluding that string and then it's
going to be sticking out from the back
similarly to how a tail would if you
would tie in a new string now once
you've made a few rows after that and
you're comfortable with your creation
you can go ahead and just snip those
strings from the back or if you're not
comfortable with that you can also just
glue them to the back of your wall
hanging so if i had an extra string
coming out from here somewhere i could
just push it down to the back of my wall
hanging and
use a little bit of glue to stick it on
and that's all about
starting your wall hanging now let's
talk about finishing it i never do
anything particularly special with my
wall hangings i just divide my base
strings into equal portions and then
just tie a simple knot at the end
and then cut them all off to be the same
length this is my preferred method of
doing it but there are plenty of other
methods out there wall hangings are very
common within the macrame world and
there's plenty of tutorials on how to
make
different endings for them within that
community as i'm not very experienced in
the topic i won't be teaching you how to
do this but i will be linking some
tutorials that i found
in the description and you can also feel
free to just search for macrame wall
hanging endings
on youtube for yourself same goes for
actually hanging your wall hanging
i've never actually done that because i
never display my works i just like
making them so i'm not particularly
experienced in this
field but because this is a very common
practice in the macrame world
there are plenty of different ways that
you can attach a string
to be able to hang your wall hanging and
once again i'm not super experienced in
this but i will be leaving links in the
description to some tutorials that i
found and you're also free to search it
up on youtube
yourself and that's it for my
explanation video on war hangings i hope
i answered your questions if you've
still got questions left over feel free
to ask them in the comments and i will
try my best to answer them as well
if you happen to be watching this in
february of 21 there is currently a
monthly challenge going in which i have
tasked you to create a wall hanging
check out my january wrap-up which i'll
link in the description of this video
for the rules on how to enter but in any
case i hope you enjoyed today's video
and before i go i want to give a special
shout out to my patrons and especially
my top supporters whose names are going
to appear on
screen thank you guys so much for your
support i truly truly appreciate it
if you also want to become a patreon
there is a link in the description where
you can sign up and get exclusive perks
for your donations it is with my patreon
support that i'm able to create these
videos so i'm massively grateful for
them
if you don't know i also have a second
channel which is masha doesn't not
same as my personal instagram handle by
the way and that second channel is
linked in the description
i recently posted a video answering
questions about what it's like to be a
youtuber i'll leave that video linked in
the card and in the description as well
for you to check out
i post non-bracelet-related
conversational type content over on that
channel and if that sounds like
something you would enjoy
i'd love to see you there but all that
being said i hope you enjoyed today's
video i hope you learned something new
from it and i will see you in my next
video
[Music]
bye
you